Guide to the Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Individuals A-L, Series I
  - Howe, Joseph
    1746/47 - Born in Killingly, CT; 1765 - Graduated from Yale College; 1765-1768 - In charge of grammar school in Hartford; 1769-1771 - Tutor at Yale; 1773 - Ordained as pastor of New South Church, Boston; 1775 - Died.
    - Two manuscript sermons, 1773-1774 (Box 214)
  - Howe, Annie Lyon
    1852- Born; 1887-1927 ABCFM missionary in Japan; 1943- Died. Founder of the Glory Kindergarten and Training School in Kobe. Additional papers of Howe are at Newberry Library, Chicago.
    - Material related to Christian Kindergartens in Japan: Government Kindergarten Rules and Regulations; Kindergarten Union of Japan - bound volume including constitution, meeting minutes, notes, financial information, Sixth Annual Report; Program materials including lesson plans, teaching aids, song, poems; Financial notes, 1907-1912, n.d. (Box 426, Folder 1-5)
    - Correspondence: from Woman's Board of Missions of the Interior to ALH re. starting ministry in Japan, incl. from M. Leake, S. Pollock, M. Wingate, 1896 Jan- 1897 Nov (Box 426, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: to ALH from M. Blatchford, P. McKay, S. Pollock, M. Wingate regarding housing, expenses in Japan and Kindergarten work, 1898-1900 (Box 426, Folder 7-9)
    - Correspondence: to ALH from K. Beam, H. Hackett, R. Stevens re. Kindergartens, 1921-1925 (Box 426, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence: to ALH from J. Atkinson, J. McKay, D. Learned, M. Shed re. housing, school in Japan, no date (Box 426, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence: ALH to Mrs. Blatchford, 1899 (Box 426, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence: K. Laurson to Dr. Gordon, 1899 (Box 426, Folder 13)
    - Collected material: commencement invitation, newsclipping, "Appeal for Kindergarten Work in France", Personal items: prayer subjects of ALH, 1917-1918, no date (Box 426, Folder 14-15)
  - Howell, Dorothy Agnes
    Dorothy Howell (1908-1983) was a church musician in eastern Pennsylvania
    - A collection of 38 lantern slides related to hymns and hymn writers, possibly used in church settings for educational purposes., no date (Box 43, Folder 1)
      The colored glass lantern slides include texts of hymns, portraits of famous hymn writers such William Cowper, Timothy Dwight, and Reginald Weber, and illustrations for hymns such as "Just As I Am, Without One Plea." Many of the slides were produced by the Wm. M. Stieren Optical Co., Pittsburgh, PA
  - Howlett family
    This may be the family of Roland Howlett, Seventh Day Adventist missionary in Vietnam in the 1940s.
    - Typed letter from "The Howletts" to Dr. Geneva Beaty-Jones, written from Giadinh, Cochinchina [Vietnam], 1941 Apr 22 (Box 303, Folder 8)
  - Hoyle, William E.
    Hoyle was a missionary of the Church Missionary Society in Uganda for 30 years. He was the first manager of the Uganda Company's General Store in Kampala in 1903. He was later resident in Khartoum, Sudan to establish a Christian bookstore there.
    - Four holograph letters with typed transcripts, written by Hoyle while in London awaiting passage to Uganda, to "Muz" (sister?) and Mr. and Miss Wolstenholme, 1903 Feb- Mar (Box 333, Folder 3)
    - Eight holograph letters / journal entries with typed transcripts, from Hoyle to his sister while on board the German East Africa Line mail steamer "Gouverneur" en route from London. Voyage was via Tangiers, Naples, Port Said, and Aden to Mombasa, 1903 Mar - Apr (Box 333, Folder 4)
    - Three holograph letters with typed transcripts, from Hoyle to his sister. Letter of April 8 written en route to Lake Victoria via newly opened Uganda Railway; describes Nairobi where he stays overnight and the journey on to Kisumu on Lake Victoria where he boards the S. S. "Winifred". Letter of April 11 written from Entebbe. Letter of April 12-16 written from Mengo, 1903 Apr (Box 333, Folder 5)
    - Letter to Cyril Ehrlich of Makerere College, Kampala re. Ehrlich' s request that Hoyle write an account of early days of Uganda Company; letter from E. H. Morland of Uganda Company (London) LTD; 4 pp. typescript by Hoyle: "The Early Days of the Uganda Company,Ltd."; Offprint of article by Hoyle: "Early Days in Kampala" from The Uganda Journal (Vol. 21, No. 1 March 1957) and Hoyle's holograph draft for the article, 1953, 1957 (Box 333, Folder 6)
    - Six holograph letters with typed transcripts, from Hoyle to his family in England while he is in Khartoum to establish a Christian bookshop., 1933 Nov - Dec (Box 333, Folder 7)
  - Hoyt, George F. G.
    - Bound volume recording sermon titles and texts, baptism, confirmations, and other information regarding services at parishes served by Hoyt during the time period 1903-1915. The majority of the records pertain to Christ Church, Lima, Ohio; Christ Church, Brooklyn, NY; St. Paul's Church, Columbia, PA. (Box 271)
  - Hudspith, Margarita Allan and Thomas
    The Hudspiths were missionaries of the Bolivian Indian Mission, which was founded in 1907 by Mr. and Mrs. George Allan and served the Quechua Indians.
    - Two photograph albums depict scenes related to the Bolivian Indian Mission, 1921-1922 (Box 53, Folder 5)
      High quality photographs with captions depict the town of San Pedro, mission churches and schools, missionary groups and conferences, Bolivian Christians, a visiting group from Moody Bible Institute, and customs and practices of Quechua Indians in Bolivia.
  - Ingalls, Rosman
    Ingalls was a Methodist missionary to the Oneida and Onondaga Indians in the Oneida District.
    - Handwritten letter from Ingalls to Nath. Jones describes his work with the Indians at the Oneida Mission in New York state, 1843 May 15 (Box 303, Folder 10)
  - Ingelet, Louis
    Le Père Ingelet served under the Missionnaires D'Afrique (Pères Blanc) in Algeria.
    - Photographs: portraits of Ingelet, group portraits with possibly family members, group portraits with colleagues and students in Algeria, scenes, unidentified individuals, ca. 1930s-1940s (Box 423, Folder 4-5)
    - Handwritten and typed letters incl. re. death of Père Ingelet (1944), his testament, letters of E. Rose to "Mademoiselle", unidentified letters; calling card of Ingelet, notice re. death of André-Bernard Ingelet, 1890-1945 (Box 423, Folder 6)
  - James, Fleming
    1877 - Born; 1921-1940 - Professor of Old Testament Literature and Interpretation, Berkeley Divinity School; 1940-1947 - Dean and Professor of Old Testament, School of Theology, The University of the South, Sewanee; 1947-1948 - Visiting Professor, Yale Divinity School; 1959 - Died.
    - Typed manuscript: "Jesus"; Bound working copy "Life of Jesus", also includes "John the Baptist", 1940-1941 (Box 427, Folder 1-3)
    - Three volumes of "Thoughts on St. Mark's Gospel"; "Notes on Acts", 1941-1944, n.d. (Box 427, Folder 4-7)
    - Two bound volumes: Course in the Psalms, 1931-1946 (Box 428, Folder 8-9)
    - Biographical information; notes by R. Lansing Hicks, n.d. (Box 428, Folder 10)
    - Collected material: The Psalter in Hebrew, annotated by JF; Hebrew Bible (Box 428, Folder 11)
  - Jeanne Marie, Sister
    Jeanne Marie, S.N.D. served with the Embakwe Mission, Convent of Notre Dame, in Southern Rhodesia.
    - Four handwritten letters from Sr. Jeanne Marie to Janet O'Neill, 1952, 1955, 1962 (Box 303, Folder 16)
  - Johnston, Geoffrey
    Johnston taught church history at Trinity College in Umuahia, Nigeria from 1963-1966. He later did missionary work elsewhere and taught in Canada.
    - Notes taken by Johnston on essays that his students at Trinity College in Nigeria wrote about the history of their home churches. These notes provide documentation about the origins and development of churches in various towns and villages in Nigeria, including Awka, Umanachi, Ikuru, Ikembara, Ugiri, Okija, Ihiala, and others.. The students who wrote the essays were primarily Anglican but also some Presbyterian and Methodist., ca. 1963-1966 (Box 423, Folder 2)
  - Judson, George W.
    1859 - Born in Stratford, CT; 1884 - B.A. Yale College; 1887 - B.D. Yale Divinity School; 1887-1892 - Minister in Orange, MA; 1898 - 1917 - Minister in Winsted, CT; 1917-1923 - Minister in Saco, ME; MInister in Huntington, Shelton, CT; 1937 - Retired.
    - Memoir: holograph and typescript copies: "Touch backs of a Midget Yankee Parson", ca. 1937 (Box 333, Folder 8)
  - Junkin, Mary
    Mary Leyburn Junkin was a Presbyterian missionary to Korea.
    - Two handwritten letters from Junkin to her aunt, written while in the U.S., 1909 (Box 303, Folder 17)
  - Kathan, Boardman
    Kathan was General Secretary of the Religious Education Association 1970-1982. See also YDSL RG 74.
    - Writings: "Luther Allan Weigle"; "The Laymen's Foreign Missions Inquiry: Christian Mission and Interfaith Reality"; "The Spiritual Journey of Abraham Lincoln", 2005, 2009, n.d. (Box 386, Folder 14)
  - Kelcey, Isaac
    Kelcey (or Kelsey) lived in Killingworth and New London, CT and kept school in the house of Joseph Nettleton.
    - Twelve ms. booklets include sermons, notes, and a list of scholars in the Nettleton school, 1754-1775 (Box 214)
  - Kidder, Daniel Parish
    1815 Oct 18 - Born in Genesee County, New York; Attended Genesee Wesleyan Seminary, Lima, New York and Hamilton College;1836 - Graduated from Wesleyan University; 1837 - Sent to Brazil to begin a new Methodist mission. From Rio de Janeiro he traveled extensively, distributing the Scriptures and tracts, and preaching; 1840 - Returned to United States following death of his wife. Served churches in New Jersey; 1844-1856 - Secretary of the Methodist Sunday School Union; 1856-1871 - Taught practical theology at Garrett Biblical Institute; 1871-1881 - Taught at Drew Theological Seminary; 1880-1887 - Secretary of Board of Education of Methodist Episcopal Church; 1891 Jul 29 - Died; Writings included: Sketches of Residence and Travel in Brazil (1845); Brazil and the Brazilians (1857).
    - Manuscript journal documenting Kidder's voyage to and work in Brazil, July 1, 1839 - Dec. 31, 1839. The journal forms a detailed record of each day's activities and of Kidder's observations on the natural history, economy, social life and other aspects of the life of the newly independent (1822) Empire of Brazil. (530 pp.) (Box 291, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript entitled "Manual of Facts Relating to the Present Condition of Brazil...Designed for the Board of Managers of the Missionary Society of the Methodist Episcopal Church..." (90 pp.), ca. 1839 (Box 291, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript journal kept by Mrs. Kidder from August 7, 1839 to March 23, 1840 (26 pp.), 1839-1840 (Box 291, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript entitled "Lectures on the Moral and Intellectual Aspect of the Empire of Brazil, Before the Lyceum Education Society of New York...14 March 1843" (20 pp.) (Box 291, Folder 1)
  - Klappert, Erich
    Missionary of the Rheinische Missionsgesellschaft in the Mentawai Islands off the west coast of Sumatra, 1953-1960.
    - Circular letter/report written from Balige, 1954 (Box 386, Folder 7)
      Material is primarily in German.
    - Circular letters/reports written from Sikakap / Pulau Mentawei, 1955-1959 (Box 386, Folder 8-10)
    - Personal letter from Klappert to Charles Forman, 1962 (Box 386, Folder 11)
    - Pamphlets written by Klappert: "Auf den Spuren der Martyrer" and "Rurusabeu - die grosse Versammlung" (Box 386, Folder 12)
    - Report of Huria Kristen Batak Protestant - "Berita Zending", 1971 (Box 386, Folder 13)
  - Kline, Carmel and Stanley
    The Klines were missionaries to the Congo serving under the Africa Inland Mission 1961-1964.
    - All correspondence is to Florence Holden from Carmel Kline: letters describe trip to Aba, Republic of Congo, where Klines previously served a term from 1944-1945, unrest due to heavy rains, 1962 Oct - Nov (Box 452, Folder 25)
    - Incl. re. housing, flooding, lack of supplies, move to Rethy, where Carmel is teaching and nursing, 1962 Jan- Oct (Box 452, Folder 26)
    - Incl. re. work in Rethy, burglaries, crime; mission station in Kwilu Province burned by boys being used by Congolese revolutionary Pierre Mulele; missionaries killed and mutilated, 1963 May - 1964 Mar (Box 452, Folder 27)
    - Incl. re. terrorist youth gangs, missionaries under house arrest, escape to Uganda, 1964 May - Sep (Box 452, Folder 28)
    - Incl. Klines arrival in Eldoret, Kenya to take charge of mission book store, atrocities of rebels, missionaries held hostage in Congo, Americans being forced to leave Kenya, 1964 Sep - Nov (Box 452, Folder 29)
    - Travel brochures re. Egypt, description of collection
  - Knock, Stanley
    Knock was a Yale Divinity School graduate who was involved in religious radio work in the New Haven area from 1948 to the early 1950s. Documentation includes scripts and commentary for "Religion at the News Desk" a weekly broadcast prepared by Protestant specialists in ethics and social sciences, based at the Yale Divinity School.
    - Re. development and operation of religious radio programming for New Haven Council of Churches (NHCC): Knock's field service while at YDS: reports, program materials, 1948-1949 (Box 405, Folder 1-2)
    - NHCC Radio Committee: policy, agendas, minutes, budgets, schedules, logs, publicity, 1948-1951 (Box 405, Folder 3-5)
    - Documentation re. general radio and television broadcasting, including survey of broadcasting in New Haven, TV workshops, ca.1950-1953 (Box 405, Folder 6-7)
    - Correspondence regarding radio programming for NHCC: letters to/from organizations, pastors, others, 1948-1952 (Box 405, Folder 8-13)
    - "Religion at the News Desk" program scripts and commentary, 1949-1951 (Box 405, Folder 14-16)
    - "Religion at the News Desk" program scripts and commentary, 1952-1955 (Box 406, Folder 17-31)
    - "WELI Church Hour" programs and schedules, 1949-1950 (Box 407, Folder 32-35)
    - "Words and Music" programs and announcements, 1949, n.d. (Box 407, Folder 36-38)
    - Miscellaneous scripts and program material for religious radio and television including "Good News Hour", "All Aboard for Adventure", "Religion for Living", 1949-1950 (Box 407, Folder 39-44)
    - Miscellaneous scripts and program material for religious radio and television including "Rhythmic Choir", spot announcements, 1949-1951 (Box 408, Folder 45-46)
    - Documentation related to religious radio course taught at Yale Divinity School by Dr. Everett Parker, 1949-1951 (Box 408, Folder 47-49)
    - YDS Christian Action organization: constitution, policy statements, speeches, newsletters, tracts, 1951-1955 (Box 408, Folder 50-51)
    - Ecumenical Continuing Education Center: internships, conferences, 1967-1969 (Box 408, Folder 52-54)
    - Material related to the New Haven Council of Churches: newsletters, clippings, annual meetings and reports, 1948-1951 (Box 408, Folder 55-57)
    - Material related to the New Haven Council of Churches: news clippings, articles, World Day of Prayer, 1950-1951 (Box 409, Folder 58-60)
    - Collected material, including thesis "The Role of Religion in the Urban University" and booklets related to religious radio, 1946-1965 (Box 409, Folder 61-62)
  - Kuck, David and Mary
    Lutheran co-workers teaching at United Theological College of the West Indies, Kingston, Jamaica
    - Circular letters, reports, 1991-2013 (Box 382, Folder 7)
    - Publications of UTCWI, 1991-1997 (Box 382, Folder 8)
  - Lansdale, H. Parker
    ale '50 B.D., '53 M.A., '56 Ph.D. A Presbyterian minister, Lansdale served the YMCA in Connecticut, Delaware, and New York.
    - "A History of Work with Youth in the YMCA - Volume I - 1900-1925" (Lansdale's Ph.D. dissertation), 1956 (Box 385, Folder 6)
    - "A History of Work with Youth in the YMCA - Volume II - 1925-1970", with cover letter, 1992 (Box 385, Folder 7)
    - "The YMCA and Christian Purpose in the Next Century" - Harold C. Smith Symposium, Silver Bay Association - edited by H. Parker Lansdale, 2000 (Box 385, Folder 8)
  - Large, Dwight Sherer
    1911 Jul 31 Born in Tekonsha, MI to Rev. Samuel W. Large and Neve B. Large; - B.A., Albion College; 1936 - Graduated from Yale Divinity School; additional graduate work at Union Theological Seminary; 1936-1952 - Served various Methodist churches in Michigan, including Clarkston, Port Huron, Kalamazoo, and Ann Arbor; 1949 - Leave of absence (from Kalamazoo) to work with American Friends Service Committee, under the UN, serving Arab refugees on the Gaza Strip; 1953-1960 - Served First Methodist Church, Germantown (Philadelphia), PA; began the "What Then Are We To Do?" sheets; 1961-1971 - Returned to Michigan, serving Lansing Central and Detroit Central; 1971 - Retired from parish ministry; 1971-1978 - Implemented Amnesty Information and Action Center, in Ann Arbor; worked with the Michigan Christian Advocate; taught Crisis Counseling at Bangor Theological Seminary; volunteered with the Inter-religious Service Board for Conscientious Objection, in Washington, DC; 1978 - Relocated to Adelaide, Australia to be near son and his family; continued to volunteer, most significantly with the Executive Committee of UNAA; 1982 Sep 18 - Died.
    - Original copies of "What Then Are We To Do?" sheets (1953 Sep 20 - 1971 May 30, 1978 Jun 18). (1 of 2 boxes), 1953-1978 (Box 272)
      These sheets were developed by Dwight Large during his parish ministry for each service and were distributed after worship as people went home. They were intended to supplement the Sunday worship service and to extend the 'church experience' throughout the week. Each sheet contains a brief summary of the sermon (50-60 words), Bible verses for each weekday, additional readings related to the sermon theme, and suggested activities to reinforce Christian awareness and growth. An index sermons (1967-1971) follows the "What Then Are We To Do?" sheets. Material donated by Mrs. Frances Large.
    - Original copies of "What Then Are We To Do?" sheets (1953 Sep 20 - 1971 May 30, 1978 Jun 18). (2 of 2 boxes) (Box 273)
  - Lathrop, Elijah
    1724 - Born in Barnstable, MA; 1749 - Graduated from Yale College; 1752-1797 - Ordained, served church in Hebron, CT; 1797 - Died.
    - Two ms. sermons dating from 1788 and 1790. Added to the 1790 sermon are a note and draft for an address, both by Charles Nichols (1790-1865), addenda dated 1844, 1788, 1790, 1844 (Box 214)
  - Lawrence, Charles
    Lawrence was based in Calcutta.
    - Handwritten letter from Lawrence to his parents describes conditions in Calcutta, including mention of missionaries, 1818 Apr 2 (Box 303, Folder 18)
  - Lawrence, Robert F.
    1810 - Born; Congregational clergyman in Claremont, New Hampshire; 1886 - Died.
    - 28 ms. sermons delivered primarily in Claremont, but also other towns in New Hampshire, Vermont, and New York, incl. Meriden, Cornish, Lebanon, Windsor, Malone, 1839 - 1861 (Box 333, Folder 12-14)
  - Lawson, Harvey Merrill
    Lawson (1868-1948) was born in Union, Connecticut, graduated from Yale University Sheffield Scientific School in 1890, and Yale Divinity School in 1893. He was appointed as a missionary of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions and, with his wife Dedi Sarah Baldwin Lawson, arrived in India in 1893 to serve under the Maratha Mission. After suffering ill health, the Lawsons returned to the United States in 1897 and Lawson served as a minister in Union, Connecticut.
    - Correspondence to Lawson from the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1892 August 6 - 1893 February 24 (Box 54, Folder 1)
      These letters provide valuable detail about the process by which Lawson applied and was accepted as an ABCFM missionary while a student at the Yale Divinity School.
    - Correspondence to Lawson from the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1893 March 2 - July 26 (Box 54, Folder 2)
      These letters provide valuable detail regarding preparations for Lawson's voyage to India as a new missionary.
    - Correspondence to Lawson from the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1893 November 10 - 1896 March 2 (Box 54, Folder 3)
      Letters relate to Lawson's health issues and his work in India, where he was stationed in the Ahmednagar area.
    - Three letters from Lawson to his wife Dedi, writing while traveling in India, 1897 January 12, 14, no date (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Sermon by Lawson and notes on sermon by George Walker in Battell Chapel, Yale, 1890 (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Two diary volumes with narrative entries covering his years as an undergraduate at Yale (1887-1889) and the first several months of 1893 prior to his departure to India, 1887, 1888, 1889, 1893 (Box 54, Folder 6)
    - Four short entry diary volumes, one documenting Lawson's activities in India and the others documenting pastoral and farming work following his return to the U.S., 1897, 1903, 1913, 1914 (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - Seven short entry diaries documenting Lawson's life in Connecticut, 1936-1938, 1940-1942, 1945 (Box 54, Folder 8-10)
  - Lefever, Ernest W.
    YDS graduate (1945); Yale Ph.D. (1956). Engaged in relief work in Europe 1945-1948 as field secretary of the World's YMCA
    - Small volume of New Testament and Psalms in German given to Lefever by Pastor Rudolf Damrath, personal chaplain to General Rommel, at a German PWO camp in Englaind in December 1945; English New Testament used by Lefever in Europe 1945-1948, signed by anti-Hitler leader Pastor Martin Niemoeller and by Jan Kucera of Prague, a Calvinist pastor who also opposed Hitler and was sent to a "reeducation camp" in Czechoslovakia by the Communist regime in 1963. (Box 423, Folder 1)
  - Lagae, Robert Constant
    Lagae (1882-1966) was a Dominican Roman Catholic vicar and bishop in the Congo from 1913. He was Vicar Apostolic of Eastern Uélé, Congo (Dem. Rep.) from 1924, Titular Bishop of Tricala from 1925 and Vicar Apostolic of Niangara from 1948.
    - Biographical documentation: newspaper clippings, biography card, death notice, photographs, 1925-1966 (Box 324, Folder 7)
    - Letters of Lagae to family members, 1924-1946 (Box 324, Folder 8)
    - Letters of Lagae to family members, 1947-1965 (Box 324, Folder 9)
    - Letters between family members that mention Robert Lagae, 1946-1950 (Box 324, Folder 10)
    - Letters between family members that mention Robert Lagae, 1925-1966 (Box 324, Folder 11)
  - Leiper, Henry Smith
    1891 Sep 17 - Born in Belmar, NJ; 1913 - B.A. Amherst College; 1917 - M.A. Columbia University; 1917 - B.D. Union Theological Seminary, NY; 1918-1922 - Missionary in China under ABCFM; 1922- - Served various organization in executive poistions, including: Commission on Missions, Congregational National Council, American Missionary Association, Universal Christian Council, Federal Council of Churches; 1938-1952 - Associate General Secretary, World Council of Churches; Executive Secretary, American Commission for WCC.
    - Letter to his parents, 1938 May (Box 199)
    - Notes taken by Leiper at the conference on drafting the constitution for the World Council of Churches in Utrecht, 1938 May (Box 199)
    - Notes taken by Leiper at the meeting of the WCC Central Committee, Chichester, England, 1949 (Box 199)
    - "The Collected Letters of Henry Smith Leiper - The China Years (1918-1922)" (Box 42, Folder 1)
      Two volumes of transcribed letters and other documents and photographs compiled by Eleanor Leiper Hall. Also available online via Presbyterian Historical Society website.
  - Lemley, H. V. and Mildred
    The Lemleys began work among the Tlapaneco Indians of Mexico in 1938 and were engaged in translation, agricultural, medical, and educational work.
    - 16 mm movie film: "The Lemleys - Among the Tlapenecos in Old Mexico, 1954" (Box 284, Folder 4)
  - Little, Charles